Robert P. "Buddy" Tinsley, Jr. collection, Inclusive: 1947-1949, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Robert P. "Buddy" Tinsley, Jr. collection
Inclusive: 1947-1949, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
518
Tinsley, Jack
10 Folders, 1 OVZ box
The Robert P. “Buddy” Tinsley collection recounts the 1947 and 1948 Baylor Football seasons through one player. Published articles, photographs, newspaper clippings, and other small memorabilia is present in the collection.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Robert Porter “Buddy” Tinsley, Jr. was born on 1924 August 19 in Damon, Texas. He was a standout football player at Barbers Hill High School in Mount Belvieu, Texas. At the age of 17 he enlisted in the Navy hoping to be a pilot, however, his size prevented this. Tinsley was stationed at Corpus Christi, Texas from 1942-1945 and was honorably discharged with the rank of sergeant.
Buddy Tinsley played college football at Baylor University from 1946-1948. He was listed as a center early in his career, but was known for his position play at both offensive and defensive tackle. In 1948, his senior season, Tinsley was named co-captain of the bruin squad and received All-Conference honors. His performance led to his 7th Round selection (54th overall) in the 1948 NFL draft by the Philadelphia Eagles.
Despite being drafted by an NFL team, Tinsley played for the Los Angeles Dons of the All-American Football Conference in 1949. After that season the AAFC went out of business, which led to Tinsley’s signing with the Winnipeg Blue Bombers of the Canadian Football League. He played eleven seasons with the Bombers, was team captain for ten years, a seven-time Western All-Star, and two-time Grey Cup winner. These honors were topped by Hall of Fame inductions by Barber’s Hill High School, Baylor Athletics, Canadian Football, and the Winnipeg Blue Bombers.
In retirement, Buddy Tinsley ran several businesses, was active with the Shriner’s, and enjoyed hunting and fishing. As a naturalized Canadian citizen, and Texan, he spent the latter years of his life wintering in Texas and summering in Canada. Tinsley was married to Hazel Stevens Tinsley until her death in 1993; they had two children, Jack and Cindy. He was remarried in 1994 to Jean Laughlin Tinsley. Buddy Tinsley died 2011 September 14 in Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada, and is buried in West Columbia, Texas.
Scope and Content
This Robert P. “Buddy” Tinsley collection includes personal memorabilia from his time as a football player at Baylor University. Items were donated by Tinsley’s children after his death. Buddy Tinsley also spent eleven seasons with the Winnipeg Blue Bombers of the Canadian Football League after his career at Baylor. Items related to that time period were donated to the Bombers organization.
Printed material in the collection includes copies of The Baylor Line and The Illustrated Football Annual. These magazines include articles about the Baylor football squad as well as mentions of Tinsley’s prowess on the field. Copies of the 1948 Baylor Yells and Songs are present in addition to a football media guide, banquet program, and Student directory.
Photographs and Memorabilia hold individual and group photos of Tinsley and other Baylor players, an original Jack Hamm newspaper cartoon drawing, and a deconstructed scrapbook. Also included is general memorabilia such as ticket stubs and pocket schedules as well as a specialized kicking shoe created for Tinsley by the University. Although Tinsley is never credited as a kicker, it is possible he performed such duties requiring the specialized shoe. Football programs and media guides of the time period omit “kicker” as an official position.
Arrangement
Prior to processing there was no arrangement. Current arrangement is in two series: I. Printed Material and II. Photographs and Memorabilia.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 518.
Related Resources
Related references
“1948 National Football League Draft.” Pro Football Hall of Fame. Accessed on 2019 August 1.
CFL.CA Staff. “Hall of Famer Buddy Tinsley Passes Away at 87.” Accessed on 2019 August 1.
Find a Grave, Inc. “Buddy ‘Big Daddy’ Tinsley.” Memorial #76582926. Databases. Accessed on 2019 August 1.
Manitoba Sports Hall of Fame. “Robert P. ‘Bud’ Tinsley.” Databases. Accessed on 2019 August 1.
The Official Site of Barbers Hill Athletics. Accessed on 2019 August 1.
“Passages: Robert Porter (Buddy) Tinsley, Jr. (Big Daddy).” Winnipeg Free Press (Winnipeg, MB), 2011 September 17.
Tait, Ed. “Buddy Tinsley Memorabilia Tells a Colourful Story.” Accessed on 2019 August 1.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Tinsley, Robert Porter, Jr., 1924-2011.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Football.; Baylor University -- Sports -- History.
Subjects
College athletes.; College Sports -- Texas -- Waco -- History.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Memorabilia.; Periodicals.; Photographs.
- Printed Material, 1947-1949; 1; 5 folders
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Printed Material series, dated 1947-1949, holds materials such as magazines, event programs and guides, Baylor Student Yells and Songs, and a student directory. The series is arranged chronologically and in good condition.
  - Baylor Line, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Illustrated Football Annual, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Yells and Songs, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Football Guide and Banquet Program, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Student Directory, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographs and Memorabilia, 1947-1948, undated; 2; 5 Folders, 1 OVZ box
  The Photographs and memorabilia series, dated 1947-1948, holds photographs, drawings, a scrapbook, and general memorabilia such as pocket schedules and ticket stubs. Also included is a kicking shoe. The series is in chronological order and in good condition.
  - General Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Cartoon Panel, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kicking Shoe, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Item 1)
  - Photo stand-up, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General Memorabilia, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)